THE LAST FANTASY
大幻影  压制:zn9213@TLF  字幕:射手
仅供交流  严禁商用
导演：简雷诺
主演：狄塔帕罗
主演：皮埃尔弗雷塞
主演：埃里克斯多海姆
片名：战地幻想曲
嘿，哈芬…
要去阿盘尼？
什么时候？
半小时以后
Hey, Halphen... Going to Epernay?
- When?
- In half an hour.
在你们卡车里边？…
带我上吧
In your truck?... Give me a ride.
当然…约瑟芬？
- Sure...Josephine?
- Of course!
当然
不单独行
- You're not the only one.
- Big deal!
大买卖
我说，马利沙…
你得接待一位长官
Say, Mar閏hal...
You have to take up a staff officer.
他来的不是时候
He's picked the wrong time.
又是约瑟芬
-Josephine again?
- Yeah, Josephine.
是啊，约瑟芬
那你会有什么收获？
Where will all that get you?
她只要等就是了
She'll just have to wait.
酒精伤人
酒精令人疯狂！
Liquor kills!
Liquor drives you crazy!
空军中队长喝它
The squadron leader drinks it!
波狄奥上尉，
这是陆军长官，分队的…
Captain de Boeldieu.
Staff officer, division...
马利沙先生你见过这幅画吗？
Do you know this photo, Mr. Mar閏hal?
当然见过，
是里科跟我弄的
Sure. Ricord took it with me.
那我哪里可找到里科先生？
And where can I find Mr. Ricord?
他休假了
那是
- On leave.
- Of course.
我担心这灰色的污迹…
This gray smudge worries me...
这里，就在这路下面
Here, just below the road.
那不是路，是条隧道
不，是铁道
- That's not a road, it's a canal.
- No, a railway.
如此一致，
是我们的空中摄影机的荣誉
Such unanimity
honors our aerial cameras.
需很大，那天
It was a foggy day.
我要解决这难题
I'd like to resolve this enigma.
我需要一架飞机
I'll request a plane.
我去准备一下，长官
I'll go get ready, sir.
飞行衣还是毛夹克？
Flying suit or fur jacket?
无特别要求
飞行衣臭，毛夹脱毛
No preference.
Flying suits smell, fur jackets shed.
空军中队战机组
Get me the fighter squadron.
开一辆车到糖加工厂
Take a car to the sugar refinery.
刚刚我击落一个科特伦战机
I just shot down a Caudron fiighter.
他们如果是长官
If they're Officers,
就邀请他们来吃午饭
invite them for lunch.
弗莱斯…
Freisler...
让我们成为你的一员
make us one of your famous
fruit punches
去庆祝我打下第十二架飞机
to celebrate the downing
of my twelfth plane.
两瓶莫西乐…
两个来恩
Three bottles of Moselle...
two Rhine...
半瓶玛特尔…
half a bottle of Martel...
三瓶香槟酒…
three bubbly...
二瓶矿泉水
two seltzer...
菠萝
pineapples...
有两个长官，一个受伤，
我已带他去医务处
Two officers. One is wounded.
I took him to the infirmary.
劳芬斯坦上尉，
21空军中队
Captain von Rauffenstein,
CO, 21 st Squadron.
玻狄奥上尉，参谋
Captain de Boeldieu, staff officer.
马利莎中校，飞行员
Lt. Mar閏hal, pilot.
My apologies.
抱歉
My officers.
我的长官们
很荣幸，我能执行法国客人
I am honored to have French guests.
现在，先生们，
我们吃吧
Now, gentlemen, let us eat.
大衣要放好！
Orderly, coats!
弗莱斯，你的酒…
Freisler, your punch...
我可为你效劳？
May I serve you?
我认识一个在柏林的玻狄奥…
I knew a Boeldieu in Berlin...
一个叫坎特玻狄奥的
是我们表兄，
埃蒙得玻狄奥
a Count de Boeldieu.
My cousin, Edmond de Boeldieu.
他是陆军武官
He was military attach?
他现在是战机飞行员
你吃吗？
He's a fighter pilot now.
Aren't you eating?
我割不了肉
I can't cut the meat.
我可以帮你吗？
谢了！
你法语很好
- May I?
- Please do.
You speak good French.
我曾在里昂做过机修工
不是开以，
我也是机修工…
I was a mechanic in Lyons.
No kidding!
Me too, I'm a mecha...
致克鲁索上尉，
法国飞行兵团
被击落于大焰中…
To Captain de Crussol,
French Flying Corps,
shotdown in flames...
属德国第21空军中队官员
From the Officers
ofthe German 21st Squadron.
我为这意外感到抱歉
I'm sorry about this coincidence.
地球啊，
保佑我们英勇的战士
May the earth lie lightly
on our valiant enemy.
我奉命带受俘长官去监房
I have orders to take custody
of the captured officers.
第17号军官战俘营
PRISONER-OF-WAR CAMP N1 7
OFFICERS' CAMP
向这些先生宣读营里的条例
Read these gentlemen
the camp regulations.
长官会依其等级受不同待遇
"Officers will be treated
with the consideration due their rank."
然而，你们要服从德国法律
"However, you are reminded
that you are subject to German law."
因此，你们要遵守德国纪律
"You therefore must obey
the rules of German discipline."
这里的任何德国士兵
有权命令你
"Any German soldier here
has the right to give you orders
你们必须无条件听从
which must be obeyed without protest."
你们要依德国军规
向长官敬礼
"You must salute Officers
according to German army regulations."
如你们试图越逃，
哨兵可奉命射杀
"If you attempt to escape,
sentries have orders to fire on officers
在营外范围发现的长官
found outside camp limits."
着装不许不当
"Incorrect dress is not permitted."
禁止聚众，
不可以侮辱德国人民
" Large crowds are forbidden.
You may not insult the German people,
不可以与营外平民通信或谈话
"or write or speak to civilians
from outside the camp."
禁止与哨兵倾谈
"It is forbidden
to speak to the sentries."
先生们，
现在进行一些例行形式
Gentlemen, we will now proceed
with some minor formalities.
俄语我词堕落跟拉丁语一样
Russian nouns are declined
just like in Latin.
新来的
去警告他们一下
- Newcomers.
- Let's warn them.
圣洁之天使，光之天使
Angel of purity, angel of light!
将你们的宝贝藏起来
Hide your valuables...
他们唱什么？
叫我们世故起宝贝
- What are they singing?
- To hide our valuables.
放手！
不要碰我！
要我的表？
Don't touch!
Those belong to me.
不要碰，这是我的
我什么也没有，伙计
I've got nothing, old man.
早知道，我就带些现金来
Had I known,
I'd have brought some cash.
这行为可不得体
This conduct is unbecoming.
Sorry, it's our duty to search you.
This is war.
对不起，这是我们的责任
去搜查你，这是战争
I perfectly agree,
but conduct it courteously.
完全同意，
但可否做理体面些
若否，我要见你指挥官
If not, I'll see
your commanding officer.
你的怎么样？
你走好去啊！
How are you - kulele?
Lucky you - calyptus!
Here, M黮ler, have some chocolate.
米勒，这里，吃点巧克力
你没打开我的火腿！
You've no right to open my ham!
规定上这么说的，
我仔细读过
烂掉了，你吃个够吧
It's in the regulations.
I read them carefully.
It's rotten! You can have it!
He's hard to please.
他挺难搞
I'm delighted when my folks
send a parcel.
家人寄包裹过来，
我感到高兴
Here we are,
in the heart of Germany,
终于到了这里，
德国中心
cut off from our families by the front,
前线将其与我们家庭分开
and here's a can of peas,
direct from Paris.
这里是一罐豆，法国来的
Is it all right?
还好吧？
真是奇迹，狱卒
对我们的包裹竟如此诚意
I'm amazed at how honest
our jailers are with our parcels.
的确，看我们的阿瑟…
It's true!
Take our feldwebel, Arthur...
他每天吃白菜，
他告诉我，胃里难受
He eats cabbage every day.
It sticks in his craw. He told me so.
他倒很愿意吃你的豆呢
He'd much rather lay into your peas.
跟自己开什么玩笑！
Don't kid yourselves.
如他们这样做，
我们就没包裹了
If they did that,
our parcels would stop coming.
他们也缺食物啊
They're short of food for themselves.
快点，我们的客人帮饿了
Hurry, our guests will be hungry.
这尝起来真糟！
This tastes like an old sock!
那些法国人吃什么？
What do they feed the French?
白菜，但他们可以有包裹
Cabbage, but they have their parcels.
那俄国人呢？
白菜根，但没包裹
- And the Russians?
- Cabbage roots, but no parcels.
那英国人呢？
And the English?
战前我做过演员…
I was on the stage before the war...
表演轻舞歌剧
in vaudeville.
有见到我吗？
剧院大难了
- Ever see me?
- Theater's too deep for me.
我较喜欢骑车运动
I prefer bicycling.
参加过法国之旅？
You follow the Tour de France?
你定听说过法布特，
加里葛，派提布莱登…
You must've heard of Fabert,
Garrigoud, Petit Breton...
我们买东西可否有喜好？
Can we purchase what we like?
可以，不过是在饭堂里
Yes, through the canteen.
啊，好！
我想买一张舒服的靠椅…
Fine, I'll buy myself
a comfortable armchair...
用来玩牌，
看书，抽烟
playing cards, a few books,
English cigarettes.
没有这些的
You won't fiind those.
这样吧，长官，
我明天再来
There you go, sir.
I'll come again tomorrow.
先生们，该吃饭了
Gentlemen, time to eat.
长官…
Sir...
先生们，我们先吃什么？
So, gentlemen,
what shall we begin with?
鸡，还是这个？
Chicken, foie gras,
还是这上尉弄的鱼？
or Captain Cook mackerel?
你个富足
You're well provisioned.
他们让我们在这里吃饭？
Don't they feed us here?
理论上如此，
但我们无法下咽
In theory, they do,
but what they give us is inedible.
好在我们有包裹，
特别有我朋友罗斯坦的
Fortunately, we have our parcels,
especially our friend Rosenthal's.
Oh, please!
唔，请吧！
A cognac to start with, sir?
先来点白兰地吧？
I've never eaten so well in my life.
我从来没吃这么少
Some fish?
来点鱼？
I'm getting used to
Rosenthal's kindness.
我都习惯罗斯坦的好意了
Man is such an adaptable creature.
你知道吗？
他是个教授…
You can see he's a professor...
教她…信仰她…
Profess her... Confess her...
跟她说话…
脱她衣服…
Address her... undress her...
Oops, a slip!
噢，打油诗！
You're quite a joker!
你真会开玩笑
Is that supposed to be witty?
这也是智慧？
He's hard to please!
噢，他挺难搞的
Let's drink to peace!
为和平而干杯！
Not bad, this cognac.
这白兰地不错
Comes from Fouquet's
in mouthwash bottles.
弗科产的，漱口水瓶装的
弗科产的？
Fouquet's?
It's a bar on the Champs-Elys閑s.
这是爱丽舍宫旁的一个酒吧
去巴黎时，
我在妹夫家吃喝，较便宜
When I went to Paris, I ate
at my brother-in-law's. It's cheaper.
最近去过巴黎吗？
上周去过
- Been to Paris lately?
- Last week.
真走运！很多人吗？
Lucky man! Places crowded?
Maxim's was packed.
马克沁机枪给堵了
I never go to places like that...
我没去过这样的地方
I prefer a nice little bar...
with good wine.
我较喜欢一个漂亮小吧…
有好酒
马克沁机枪…
也不知道这个
- Maxim's... don't know it either.
- It's no great loss.
无关紧要
We know you eat
at your brother-in-law's...
我们知道
你在你妹夫家里吃…
他永远都不放松点！
He never lets up!
莫那科先生在这吗？
Is he there, "Mr. Monocle"?
No, he's not.
不，不在！
I've just been to the canteen.
It's about his armchair request...
我刚去过餐厅，
是他要张靠椅…
Let him tighten his belt!
让他系紧他的带子
I'll tell him.
我会告诉他的
拿包裹的那个人不错，
很有钱吧？
He's nice, the guy with the parcels.
Well off?
那又怎样？
你知道罗斯坦银行吗？
And how!
You know the Rosenthal bank?
His parents.
是他的父母
Am I tickling you?
我弄痒你了？
他是干什么的？
- And what's he do?
- Runs a big fashion house.
他开有一家大时装店
Funny.
With his money, I wouldn't...
有意思，有他的钱，
我可不…
What do you do in civilian life?
你平常做什么？
I'm a engineer for the cadaster.
我是卡达斯特的一个工程师
Sure, the cadaster...
噢，是卡达斯特…
就我们之间…
我们可以信任你的伙伴，
那个上尉吗？
噢，他看起来有点怪，
但还可以
你们可以相信他
好吧
为什么呢？
天黑后，我们挖遂道，
你知道吗？
just between us...
can we trust your pal, the Captain?
He may seem strange,
but he's okay.
You can trust him all right.
- It's all right, then.
- Why?
You see, after dark...
we're digging a tunnel.
What for?
为什么呢？
To escape.
越狱啊
What do you dig with?
用什么来掘土？
A coal shovel, old food cans...
煤铲，旧罐头…
I calculate
we should come up in a garden
我估计我们会走到一个花园
就在那些建筑后面
那里是开阔的乡村
那很慢啊
behind those buildings there.
It's open country.
That's slow work.
我们挖了两个月了
We've been at it for two months.
just a few more weeks...
再过几周…
战争先结束了
不要这么灰心
The war'll be over fiirst.
You're deluding yourself.
是吗？
最好有所准备
Think so?
Best to be prepared.
Where's the tunnel?
隧道在哪里？
You'll see tonight, after roll call.
晚上点我后，
你就知道了
So you're digging a hole...
像蒙特克里斯托
Like Monte Cristo. What a laugh!
真好笑
- Thanks for the wash.
- You can't do it with your arm.
谢谢你帮我说
你可以用手臂洗的
Mind if I ask you something?
介意我问你些问题吗？
Go ahead.
问吧
What's a "cadaster"?
"卡达斯特"是什么？
- Mar閏hal.
马利沙
到！
玻狄奥！
是玻狄奥上尉
卡迪尔
这里！到我啦！
- Present.
- Boeldieu.
- Captain de Boeldieu.
- Cartier.
- Here...we go again!
晚安，阿瑟
Good night, Arthur!
轮到谁了？
- Whose turn is it?
- Cartier's.
卡迪尔了
那是干什么的？
What's that for?
呼吸用的
For breathing.
These are to extend the line.
这些用来延长拉线
And the bags?
那袋呢？
For removing earth.
移走泥土的
这是警报装置
This is the alarm.
如我感到窒息
If I start to suffocate,
I yank on the string...
我就拉这线
The can falls...
这罐头就掉下来
然后你们将我拉出来
And the boys pull me out by the feet...
拖着我的腿
The feet...
腿！
还等什么？
What are you waiting for?
看我表演吧
Watch me play the mole...
打洞啦！
mol-asses!
隧道安全吗？
Is the tunnel safe?
用木块筑起来了
It's shored up with wood
from the theater.
木块从剧院拿来的
And the earth?
那土呢？
填在地板下面
Stuffed under the floorboards.
但没有地方了
现在我们用袋装土
在出操时，我们再倒掉它
But there's not an inch of space left.
Now we fiill bags and empty them
during exercise.
嘿，听到吗？
我肯定听到什么
Hear that?
I'm sure I heard something.
没有啊
听
It's nothing.
Listen...
我们叫人去看一下
你看起来天真点
去看一下
我会装着去厕所
We'll send someone out
to check.
You've got an innocent face.
Go take a peek outside.
I'll pretend to go to the latrine.
嘿，亚瑟，发生什么事了？
Say, Arthur, what happened?
这家伙想逃跑
The fellow tried to escape.
我们在花园里捉住他
We caught him in the garden
behind those buildings...
就在那些建筑后面
We opened fire.
我们开了枪
Behind the buildings?
那些建筑后面？
他死吗？
- Is he dead?
- I think so.
我想是的
And you, what are you doing out?
你在这里干什么？
在厕所
Going to the latrine.
怎么了？
- What was it?
- Someone tried to escape.
有人想逃跑
他到花园那么远呢？
在那些建筑后面
一个哨兵，打中他了
He got as far as the garden
behind the buildings.
A sentry shot him.
他死了
He's dead.
警报器！
The alarm!
没有声音
拖他出来
- No answer.
- Pull him out.
伤得很重？
Hurt bad?
喝些白半地
Drink some cognac.
弗科产的
From Fouquet's.
你眼中有泥
不要把瓶掉了
Here's mud in your eye.
Don't drop the bottle.
明天谁下去？
Who goes down tomorrow?
你了，长官，
如果你不介意
荣幸，我懂怎样在矿下爬
You do, sir... if you don't mind.
My pleasure. I understand
crawling is fine exercise.
再提醒一次，严禁
I remind you it is strictly forbidden
接受非军式服装
to receive non-military clothing.
好消息吗？
Good news?
是我阿姨的，
她住博托斯
It's from my aunt in Bordeaux.
People are swarming into town.
人们蜂拥至城镇
有什么想法？
What do you think?
他们最好小心
They'd better watch out,
德国人称之为一大突破
没有响铃，
所以不会有太大意思
去做些园林活？
the Germans are claiming
a major breakthrough.
There's been no bell-ringing
so it can't mean much.
Up for some gardening?
我讨厌德国人的公告牌，
总是夸张
I hate the way
German bulletins exaggerate.
我们报纸就不是啦？
And our papers don't?
还记得俄国的
"蒸汽压路机"
Remember the "Russian steamroller"?
是时候做些正经事了吧？
Isn't it time we got down
to serious business?
是，但不是突而其来
Sure, but not all at once.
那有我的大"冬季"
And that famous General "Winter,"
小气的科劳人怕死它了
so lethal to the nasty Krauts
对盟军都很有用
but so tonic to the Allies...
你还记得"特宾尼特"？
And do you remember "Turpinite"?
一个烧瓶，小萝卜大小
A flask the size of... a radish
that could blow up a whole battalion.
可以炸坏一个军营呢
They even tried it on a flock of sheep.
他们在一群羊上试过呢
他们不收手，太坏了
Too bad they didn't stop at that.
你们在种些什么？
- What're you guys planting?
- Dandelions.
蒲公英！
我梦想吃蒲公英沙律呢
你的蒲公英长成前
战争已结束了
I'm dreaming of dandelion salad.
The war'll be over
before your dandelions grow.
这劳动会使我们的手变壮
This singular exercise
will give us workman's hands.
树干在这里
The trunks are here!
制服？  剧院里呢
- The costumes?
- At the theater.
应该有一个
放妇女衣服树干
There should be a trunk
with women's clothes.
来吧，长官？
Coming, sir?
我理论技巧不行
My theatrical skills are questionable.
Besides, I'm engaged.
再者，我订婚了
玩耐性？
正是，我是现实主义者
- Playing patience?
- Exactly. I'm a realist.
找到什么没有？
阿瑟？
Find anything, Arthur?
我什么也没有
Nothing.
好吧，先生们，
玩得开心点吧！
Well, gentlemen, enjoy yourselves.
我们把这些放哪？
Where will we put all this?
我去要些钩来
I asked for hangers.
小心点
Be careful...
这些东东要小心爱护
These things
should be handled with care...
要闭上眼睛
with your eyes closed.
看起来小女孩的衣服
Looks like a little girl's dress.
现在的衣服是短的了
Dresses are short now.
刚盖女膝而已
just below the knee.
我听到了，
我爱看到它！
So I hear. I'd love to see that!
那就穿上它吧
Then put it on.
不行，他从来不刮胡子
Not him, he never shaves.
迈森男，
你长得像天使
有什么好玩的？
- You have an angel face, Maisonneuve.
- Anything to amuse.
我们得拿清单
We have to take inventory.
也有女紧身胸衣！
The corset, too!
别激动
Take it easy.
不单是衣服
It's not only the dresses.
They wear their hair short, too.
她们也留短衣
短发
Short hair!
就像跟一个男孩睡觉一样
It's like sleeping with a boy!
我们不在时，
女人变得很傻
我担保妻子没有剪短头发
When we're not around,
women act foolish.
I'm sure my wife hasn't cut her hair.
那是高档妓女才干的
你怎样知道的？
That's for high-class floozies.
How would you know,
with that mug?
鞋！
它们多小啊！
长袜子
纯丝长袜！
嘿，伙计，
我准备好了！
我们先梦想一下吧
- Shoes!
- How small they are!
Stockings.
Stockings of sheerest silk!
Hey, fellas, I'm ready!
Let us dream a bit first.
你只会捣鬼
You'll only stifle our imagination.
看这个！
黑长袜
Look at that!
Black stockings!
看起来真像个女孩
Looks like a real girl!
滑稽吧
Funny, huh?
看起来很滑稽吧
Doesn't it look funny?
的确，很滑稽
Yeah, sure looks funny.
可怜的孩子
Poor boys.
玩得尽兴
Enjoy yourselves.
外面孩子与士兵玩呢
Out there, children play soldier...
这里面是士兵像孩子般玩
In here, soldiers play like children.
要知道家里怎样就好了
I wish I knew what's going on
back home.
没新闻？
没有
- No news?
- Nothing.
我不在乎
我的太太在做什么
I don't care what my missus is up to.
我想出去，因为我烦透了
烦透了
I want out
'cause I'm bored stiff... bored!
所以你想逃，追求这一乐趣
So you want to escape for the fun ofit.
Right!
对
For me, it's the spirit
of contradiction.
于我而言，是矛盾的精神
他们不让我战斗
They won't let me fiight,
so I'm dying to.
我快死了
我讨厌在这儿
这里别人整天与尘土打交道
我可觉简单了
高尔夫球场是打高尔夫球的
网球场是打网球的
I hate being here
when others are biting the dust.
For me it's simple.
A golf course is for golf.
A tennis court for tennis.
监狱是用来越逃的
而你，罗斯坦，
是个运动者
A prison camp is for escaping.
And you, Rosenthal, the sportsman...
他？他出生在耶路撒冷
不，是在维也纳，
母亲是丹麦人
父亲是波兰人，
法语说很好
旧时的凯特人贵族
Him? He was born in Jerusalem.
No, in Vienna. To a Danish mother
and a Polish father, naturalized French.
Old Celtic aristocracy!
但你的法国根
Yet for all your French roots, none
of you owns an acre ofyour country.
却没有一寸你国家的土地
In 35 years,
the Rosenthals have acquired
35年内，
罗斯坦一家就获得了
three chateaux with hunting preserves,
三个城堡，
兔场，种马饲养场
farms, orchards, warrens, stud farms,
还有三个真真的祖先画廊
and 3 galleries of bona fiide ancestors.
那总算值得逃狱了吧
If that's not worth escaping
to fight for!
我倒没想过
爱国主义可这样看
I'd never considered patriotism
from such an unusual angle.
有那些猎场
With all those game preserves,
你的猎狗真得填得满满的
your lackeys must
really stuff themselves.
我很奇怪地就卷入了战争
I got into the war in a funny way.
因为吃素，
我就成了士兵
I became a soldier
because I'm a vegetarian.
不错，我和我妈胃不好
That's right.
My brother and I had stomach ailments.
医生叫我们不要吃肉
The doctor warned us
against eating meat.
我就吃素，长得好好的
I turned vegetarian and got well.
我母亲，继续吃肉
My brother went on eating meat,
就病了，接着死掉了
got sick and was invalided out.
你信奉素食主义，
并不是义务所致
Your citations show vegetarianism
didn't interfere with duty.
或者我妻子不再欺骗我
Or stop my wife from cheating on me.
你觉得这很烦人吧
You have to admit it's stirring.
我讨厌横留
I loathe fifes.
当然，你听见了嘛
Still, it gets to you.
不是音乐的缘故
It's not the music that gets to you...
是操步的脚
It's the marching feet.
真多谢你的废话
我们裤子弄坏了
Thanks to your dumb talk
I ruined my pants...
杜奥蒙特要塞被占领
FORT DOUAUMONT TAKEN!
我们的表演怎样？
What about our show?
Do we still put it on?
还要上演吗？
你打赌吧，我们定会上演的
理由充分着呢！
You bet we do!
All the more reason.
事实上我们应该
邀请德军官来看
In fact we should invite
the German Officers.
in your artistic endeavors, Mar閏hal,
尽管我不会加入
到你的表演中去
马利沙
恭贺你，这就是精神
Although I won't join
let me congratulateyou...
That's the spirit!
你们见过玛格丽了吗？
Have you met Marguerite
She's neither tall nor petite
她不高也不娇小
With eyes that glow, skin like snow
And lips in a cupid's bow
眼睛闪亮，皮肤雪白
嘴唇呈弓形
呵，当这神圣的生物
听到我热情的宣言
Well, when this divine creation
Heard my ardent declaration
她给我一朵玫瑰
She gave me a rose, tweaked my nose
Saying, "I'll give you joy"
拧着我鼻子
说"我给你快乐"
我说："还是表示感谢"
I said, "Thanks all the same
But that's not why I came"
但那不是我来的原因
如你想给我快乐
If you want to give me joy
玛格丽，玛格丽
如你想给我快乐
让我做给你的爱人
Marguerite, Marguerite
If you want to give me joy
Make me your loverboy
我在她窗下等待
然后我唱小夜曲
"我的灵魂是
坏供燃烧的木料"
因为你们眼睛让我的心着火
所以这甜蜜的可人女子
扑灭我狂怒的火焰
一个桶从她窗台倾泻，问：
"还在燃烧吗？"
'Neath her window I waited
And then I serenaded::
"My soul's apyre
since your eyes set my heart on fire!"
So this sweet and caring dame
To put out my raging flame
Did a bucket spill from her sill
Asking, "Is it burning still?"
我说："还是表示感谢"
I said, "Thanks all the same
But that's not why I came"
但那不是我来的原因
If you want to give me joy
玛格丽，让我做你的情人
Marguerite, let me be your loverboy
现在大家一起来
All together now!
现在…从巴黎来的！
And now... direct from Paris!
接住，亚瑟
Get it, Arthur?
停演！停演！
Stop the show! Stop the show!
停止！伙计们
Stop, fellas!
我们又夺回杜奥蒙特
We've retaken Douaumont!
It's in the German papers.
德国报纸上写着呢
一个小洞，用来逃狱的
A little hole, to escape.
德军占领杜奥蒙特
GERMAN TROOPS
RECAPTURE DOUAUMONT
这不是很糟糕吗？
Isn't that awful?
有什么可剩下的
Can't be much left of it!
放手
Get off my back!
I can't take it any more! I'm fed up!
我再也受不了啦
我烦透了
I want to see some light!
我要见些光！
这时臭气熏天！
听到吗？这里臭气熏天！
我要听声音
It stinks of shit in here!
Hear me? It stinks of shit!
And I want to hear a voice.
我想听法国话的声音
I want to hear a French voice.
他在叫什么？
这战争大长了！
如果我估计准确
我们可在四天后控制花园墙
很多泥啊！
现在我们就要离开这里了
What was he yelling about?
The war's too long.
If my calculations are right,
we should be under the garden wall
in four days.
That's a lot of dirt!
Now that we may get away
再次回到家
and reach home again,
I'm afraid of what's waiting for me.
我害怕等着我的东西
天下何处无芳草！
这不适合我
There's more than one woman on earth!
Not for me.
这就是她欺骗你的原因
That's why she cheats on you.
leaving Mar閏hal behind.
有一东西，我很担心
把马利沙留在后面
我也觉得沉重
One thing upsets me:
It weighs on me as well.
实际上，这很烦人
In fact... it disturbs me.
但这是战争，
可没感情可言
But that's war. No room for sentiment.
老伙计，见到你真好
Glad to seeyou, old man.
我们也是
We are, too.
Wait until you hear why.
等我们告诉你为什么吧
You old dog!
你这老伙计
有没有可以吃的？我饿了
Got anything to eat? I'm hungry.
坐下吧，
罗斯坦在准备点食物
Have a seat.
Rosenthal's getting some grub ready.
几点了？
What time is it?
11点了！
11 o'clock.
今天时间过得很慢
Time's dragging today.
的确，但今晚就是
"再见"（德）了！
Sure, but tonight it's aufwiedersehen!
我们就在亚姆斯特丹碰面？
So, we meet in Amsterdam?
我希望见到荷兰，看郁金香
I'm keen to see Holland,
for the tulips.
这些奶酪怎办？
What about the cheese?
Don'tyou like Dutch cheese?
你不喜欢荷兰奶酪吗？
喜欢
但他们说
郁金香地延伸几英里
你骨子里是逛街女孩的东西
Sure, but they say the tulip fiields
stretch for miles.
You have the instincts of a shop girl.
三点集合
Assembly at three o'clock.
所有官员都要挖营
All Officers are to change camps.
准备好东西
Get your things ready.
先生们，旅途愉快
Gentlemen,
I wish you a pleasant journey.
希望你们尽快再见到妻子们
I hope you will see
your wives again soon.
我们在让他们提高警惕
We ought to alert them.
有关那隧道的
About the tunnel.
先生，
在七号营房有一隧道
Sir, there's a tunnel in Barrack 7.
把窗开了
这里臭死了
Open the window.
It stinks in here!
长官，我可否指出一下
Sir, may I point out there are
only two pairs of white gloves left.
只剩两对白手套了
We can't get any gloves here.
这里我们得不到手套
Try to make them last.
尽量久用吧
是，长官，还要咖啡吗？
Yes, sir... More coffee, sir?
如果你管这鬼东西叫咖啡
If you call this muck coffee,
I have to accept it.
我认了吧
至少，它令我暖和
At least it warms my insides.
新牢房人员我单，长官
The list of new prisoners, sir.
三我新官员来报到，长官
Three new officer POWs reporting, sir!
很高兴再次见到你，玻狄奥
Delighted to see you again, Boeldieu.
我很抱歉在这里与你会面
But I'm sorry to see you here.
我们也这样认为
We feel the same.
坐下吧，先生们
Sit down, gentlemen.
No, thank you, sir.
不坐了，谢谢，长官
As you wish.
随你吧
玻狄奥上尉
Captain de Boeldieu,
四次试图越营
four escape attempts:
利用垃圾筒的加热管
Through a heating duct,
in a garbage bin,
利用排水道，在洗衣篮里边
via the sewers,
in a laundry basket.
有时，人须降格一点
One must lower oneself,
at times.
我明白
I understand.
Lieutenant Mar閏hal,
马利沙中校
五次试图越营
伪装成扫烟囱的
five attempts at escape:
Disguised as a chimney sweep...
有改正，长官
是加热工程师
伪装成一我德军士兵
伪装成一我妇女
Correction, sir:
heating engineer.
Disguised as a German soldier,
disguised as a woman.
有趣，真有趣
可当军士想抓住我时，
并不有趣
我不喜欢这个
Amusing, very amusing.
But less so when an NCO
tried to pick me up. That I didn't like!
Indeed?
真的？
I assure you.
我向你保
狄莫得中尉，
三次试图…
Lieutenant Demolder,
three attempts...
先生们，
我对你们的爱国热忱
Gentlemen, I respect
your patriotism and courage.
及勇气表示尊敬
但这里的情形有根本的不同
But the situation
is completely different here.
没人能从这城堡中逃出去
No one escapes from this fortress.
你理解吧？
You understand me, don't you?
所以为了避免受责
So as not to be accused
of German barbarism,
说我滥用德国暴行
我决定施行法军条例
I have decided to apply
French regulations.
仔细阅读一下这个
Look them over.
很好的睡前读物
They make good bedtime reading.
现在，先生们，你们可跟我…
And now, gentlemen,
if you will follow me...
奥思瓦，我的大衣
Oswald! My coat.
我这些士兵不年轻了
My soldiers aren't young,
但他们很会玩这个
but they enjoy playing soldier.
我们还有多25支这样的枪
We have 25 more guns like this one.
我想你们知道
这马克沁机枪吧？
I suppose you know the Maxim gun?
很了解，长官
Very well, sir.
但我较中意饭馆
But I prefer the restaurant.
Touch?
我倒想起十五岁时
识的一个女孩
她叫菲菲
她死了？
十二世纪
12th century.
对不起，长官！
Excuse me, sir...
这小屋是否为
玻狄奥上尉和我特制的？
Was this villa built specially
for Captain de Boeldieu and myself?
只有我们才是你的世界？
Are we your only boarders?
不，你的同志在那后面
Your comrades are back there.
1 3th century.
十三世纪
有120英尺高
A 1 20-foot drop.
谢谢你带我们参观这里
So kind of you
to show us around the grounds.
这城堡很好，长官
It's such a nice castle, sir.
它如此老了…
It's so old...
如此激奋人心
And so cheerful.
抱歉不能给你自己一间房
Sorry I can't give you
a room to yourself.
我很感动，但…
我永远不会接受
I'm touched,
but I'd never have accepted.
但愿这次步行没有累着你
I hope our walk
didn't weary you too much.
没有，长官，我们挺好的
Not at all, sir, we're fiine.
十四世纪    纯哥特式的
- 14th century.
- Pure Gothic.
先生们，如不介意…
Ifyou don't mind, gentlemen...
你们的朋友罗斯坦中尉
Your friend Lt. Rosenthal,
from the Hallbach camp, is here.
从哈巴赫来的，在这里
哦，老罗斯坦！
他一样不走运
指挥官将你们都放进同一间
- Not old Rosenthal!
- He wasn't any luckier.
The commandant has put you all
in the same room.
这样你们吃得好些
他真不赖
That way you'll eat better.
That's very nice of him.
只是个形式而已
A mere formality.
我跟一个浅黑女子捉获的
- I caught it with a brunette.
- Who can you trust?
你可信谁啊！
是我母亲的一个朋友
很值得尊敬，
做慈善工作的
好社会里边，
它通常表现为天花
A friend of my mother's.
Quite respectable. She did charity work.
In good society it's usually the pox.
Right, Boeldieu?
对吧，玻狄奥？
The pox used to be our privilege.
But we've lost it.
天花曾是我们的特权
但我们已丢掉它了
Like so many others.
跟许多其他东西一样
Everything is popularized.
什么东西都变得大众化了
Cancer and gout
aren't working-class diseases,
癌与痛风并非工人阶级病
but they will be, believe me.
但会是的，信我吧
How about intellectuals?
那知识分子呢？
With us it's tuberculosis.
我们的是肺炎
Here's Mr. Pindar.
平达先生来了
And the middle class?
和中产阶级？
肝，肠脆弱
Liver and intestinal ailments...
They eat too much.
他们吃得太多了
We'd each die
ofour own class diseases,
我们会死得其所的
if war didn't make all germs equal.
如果战争没有创造出平等
Your dictionaries are in myway.
你的字典挡着我了
Excuse me,
不好意思
but Pindar has always been
so badly translated.
但平达总是被译得这么差
真值得哀悼
我真抱歉
我也不在意
但这平达是何人？
继续玩笑！
但平达对我至关重要…
比你重要，在战争，
我的一生！
平达是最伟大的希腊诗人
最伟大的希腊诗人？
你不是说…
看！我的图画马上就好了
看，这是我们所在地…
A lamentable oversight.
I'm so sorry.
Not that I care,
but who's this guy Pindar?
Go on,joke! But Pindar
means more to me than anything...
More than you, the war, my life!
Pindar is the greatest Greek poet.
The greatest Greek poet?
You don't say...
There! My map'sjust about finished.
See... this is where we are...
这弯口上16英里处，
位于梅思河
16 miles above this bend
in the Main River.
到达康斯坦湖上的瑞士
To reach Switzerland
above Lake Constance
避开莱因河
and avoid the Rhine,
we'd have to travel...
我们得走过…
- 200 miles.
- No kidding!
200英里！
不是开玩笑！
这意味着走15夜
每天只吃6块糖，
2块饼干
你和你的地图
你就跟他和他们的平达
一样疯狂
逃营…
这里，图画画完了！
"公正搜寻罪恶"
还可以吧
看，要到这康斯坦…
That means walking 15 nights on 6 lumps
of sugar and 2 biscuits a day.
You and your map, you're as crazy
as him and his Pindar. To escape...
There! My picture's finished.
"Justice Pursuing Crime."
It came out all right.
Look, to reach this Constance place...
它靠得住吗？
Will it hold?
它可耐10个你和5个像我的人
It can hold 10 of you and 5 like me.
他们在检查房间！
They're searching the rooms!
放到毯下面，快点！
- Under the mattress, quick!
- No, under mine!
放到矿上面
That won't do.
这不行
It's childish.
这真幼稚
我可以拿吗？
May I?
我有个主意
Now there's an idea!
A convenient little gutter.
小条便利的水槽
他们来了
Here they are!
先生们，查房！
Gentlemen... inspection.
"路易写给维克多："
"Louise wrote to Victor:
"经22个爱之夜后"
I am as weary as a girl
after 22 nights oflove."
"我像女孩般倦怠"
22个爱之夜，想一想！
22 nights oflove, imagine that!
Continue!
继续查！
不是那角落
Not that corner!
向我保
Give me your word that you've nothing
in here against regulations.
人们这里没有违规的东西
You have my word.
我向你保
但为什么要我保  ，
而非他们的？
But why my word and not theirs?
别人的保
The word of a...
Rosenthal...
像罗斯坦…
and a Mar閏hal?
和马利沙的？
It's as good as ours.
他们的跟我们的一样
Perhaps.
或许如此吧
不，不要这样
No, not that!
这很稀有的
It's very rare.
可怜的老平达！
Poor old Pindar!
他们真是十足的傻瓜
They really are stupid.
这里一切安好？
Everything go all right in here?
还不赖
我们的也是
- Not bad.
- For us, too.
你的表兄，
埃蒙得玻狄奥怎样了？
And how is your cousin,
Edmond de Boeldieu,
我在柏林碰见的武官？
the military attach?I met in Berlin?
他干得不赖，他很快活
He's doing well. He's very happy.
他丢了条手臂，
娶了有钱女人
He lost an arm
and married a rich woman.
真不赖
A truly fine career.
Recognize her?
认得她吗？
当然认得
1919年在利物浦
我们曾一起骑马来着
我还记得呢
Sit down.
坐下吧
Let me tell you something...
我跟你说点话
相信我
Believe me,
我现在的作用
我感到极为反感
my present functions
revolt me as much as they do you.
跟你们感觉一样
That's being harsh.
那太辛苦了
I used to be a combatant.
我曾是个战士
我现在是个官僚，
一个警察
Now I'm a bureaucrat, a policeman.
但只有这条路
But it's the only way
我可以看起来仍显得…
I can still appear to be
效忠于我的祖国
serving my fatherland.
我烧掉了所有的东西
I have burns all over...
That explains my gloves.
你明白手套的事了吧
My spine is fractured in two places.
我脊柱有两处破裂了
A silver plate.
一块银色的碟子
In my kneecap, too.
也在我的膝盖骨里边
I owe these riches
to the misfortunes ofwar.
我将这归咎于战争的不幸
- May I ask you a question?
- Of course.
我可以问你一个问题吗？
问吧
Why did you make
为什么你使得…
an exception ofme
我成为一个例外
by inviting me here?
将我邀请来这儿呢？
因为你叫玻狄奥
是法军中的职业军官
而我是劳芬斯坦
是德帝国军队的职业军官
但我的同志也是军官
A Mar閏hal and a Rosenthal, Officers?
马利沙和罗斯坦，军官？
Because your name is Boeldieu,
career offiicer in the French Army.
And I am Rauffenstein, career offiicer
in the German Imperial Army.
But my comrades are Officers, as well.
They're fine soldiers.
他们是好兵士
Charming legacy
of the French Revolution.
这法国革命的遗产真迷人
Neither you nor I
can stop the march of time.
你我都不能阻住时间步伐
Boeldieu...
玻狄奥…
I don't know who will win this war,
我不知谁会打赢这局战争
but whatever the outcome,
但无论结果如何
但意味着
劳芬斯坦和玻狄奥的…
完结
不再有人需要我们
这难道不可惜吗？
可能吧
it will mean the end of
the Rauffensteins and the Boeldieus.
We're no longer needed.
Isn't that a pity?
Perhaps.
我欣赏你照料天竺葵的方式
I admire the way
you tend your geranium.
不要以为我成了植物学家
Don't think I've become a botanist,
但它是城堡里唯一的花
but it's the only flower
in the fortress.
这里除了常春藤和麻，
什么也不长
Nothing grows here but ivy and nettles.
很高兴我能跟你们一起走
I'm glad I'm leaving with you.
跟我们
With us.
的确，我喜欢玻狄奥，
但是…
Sure, I like Boeldieu, but...
With him...
和他…
I never really feel at ease.
我从未感到轻松过
Different backgrounds...
There's a wall between us.
背景不同，
我们之间隔着堵墙
He's a terrifiic guy.
他棒极了
Sure, and he's on the level, but...
唔，他坦率，
但是…
Suppose you and I were on the skids.
假如我和你同在滑橇上
We'd just be two bums.
我们只能是叫化子
If it happened to him,
如果变做他如此
he'd still be " Monsieur de Boeldieu."
他仍会是：玻狄奥先生
Anyway, you've been terrifiic, too,
无论怎样，你也很棒
feeding us with your parcels.
能用你的包裹执行我们
That's all vanity.
只是虚荣罢了
I'm really proud to come
from a rich family.
我很得意我家里富裕
Inviting you to my table
is myway ofshowing it.
邀你吃饭，
我就可让你知道了
Most people think we're stingy.
很多人以为我吝啬
Wrong. We're often generous.
错了，我们常显得大方
Unfortunately, along with that quality,
很不幸，
却带上了那东西
Jehovah gave us an overdose of pride.
约赫华太过纵容我们自大了
To hell with Jehovah!
约赫华去死吧
我只知道你是个好伙计
All I know is you've been a real pal.
我们收到一个大柳条箱
We've received a large crate,
是我们女沙皇的礼物
a gift from our Czarina.
来，我们一起分享
Please come and share it with us.
女沙皇的礼物？
肯定是鱼子酱
From the Czarina? Must be caviar.
玻狄奥，你也来吧？
他们有伏特加
- Coming, Boeldieu? They've got vodka.
- Vodka? Lead on.
伏特加？带路
现在我们补偿你全盘好意了
Now we can pay you back
for all your kindness.
女沙皇总是好心肠
The Czarina is always good-hearted.
你的女沙皇，
好一位女士
Quite a lady, your Czarina.
猜里面有什么！
Think of what's in store!
"代数学原理"…
"道德基础"…"语法"
"Principles ofAlgebra"...
"Elementary Ethics"... "Grammar"...
烹调书
A cook book!
什么老掉牙的书啊
Something to sink your teeth into!
这是什么日子啊
What a farce!
趁没发生什么，我们还是走吧
Let's go before something happens.
再见，不过还是感谢了
Goodbye, thanks anyway.
哥萨克人来劲了
我们快离开这儿！
- The Cossacks aren't happy!
- Let's get out of here!
你没权烧书
You have no right to burn books!
给我们送书，
真是疯了
It's crazy sending us books!
哨兵正忙着对付俄国人呢
The sentries are busy with the Russians.
这里下去挺久的，
但没哨兵
It's a long drop here,
but it's unguarded.
我们要是准备好，
就可以逃了
If only we'd been ready!
What a chance!
多好的机会
特别是晚上
- Especially at night!
- We'll try again.
我们再试一次
他们预先给我们排练了一下
太好了
现在我们知道
一个人可担搁他们五分钟
他的同志就可逃跑了
太危险了！
你在夸大其辞
我会觉得有趣的
It was kind ofthem
to hold a rehearsal for us.
Now we know if one man
can divert them for 5 minutes,
his comrades can escape.
- Too risky!
- You're exaggerating.
It would amuse me.
When do you want to go?
你什么时候想走？
为什么我们？
你也在我们之列？
Why us? You're in it, too.
不
Why not? Don't you trust us?
为什么？
你不相信我们？
- That wouldn't stop me.
- Well then?
不是这个
那是什么？
A plan like yours
can only work with two men.
你的计划只够两个人用
And I know your preference.
而我知道你的喜好
这不公平
- It's not fair.
- What's fair in war?
战时讲什么公平？
We can't accept that.
我们不能接受
I'm not asking you...
我不是问你…
I'm telling you.
我在告诉你
The arts aren't forbidden here.
这里不禁止艺
You like music?
你喜欢音乐？
So-so... I like a good waltz.
一般…
我喜欢好的华尔兹
I love the flute.
我喜爱长笛
Here's the program:
We buy flutes for everyone.
这是计划
我们给每人都买一长笛
On the given day:
concert in all the rooms at 5 p.m.
特定的一天：
下午五点房间音乐会
That's when night falls.
那时天黑了
Five minutes later,
they confiiscate our flutes.
五分钟后，
他没收了笛子
At 5:1 5,
五点15分时
another concert
with anything at hand:
另一个音乐会，
什么拿来用了
saucepans, animal noises,
平底锅，动物噪声
grinding teeth, whatever...
磨牙，什么都有
Result: assembly in the courtyard.
结果：庭院里集体
Then what?
然后怎样？
这是我关心的问题
That's my concern.
You'll have fiive minutes...
你清洁墙壁和到林子那里
to clear the walls and reach the woods.
Look, Boeldieu,
看，玻狄奥
我不知道该怎么说
I don't know how to put it,
but I feel awful about this.
但我感到这可怕
- Come now!
- Yes, awful.
振作点  真的，很可怕
我想说点什么…
I'd like to say something...
Pour some warm water
over my gloves, will you?
倒点热水到我手套上，好吗？
无论发生什么事情
Whatever happens,
I want you to know that...
我想，你知道…
I'm not doing this for you personally.
我不是为你私人效劳
So we needn't get mawkish.
所以我们不必假作多情
Go on.
再多点
But there are times in life...
但有时生命中有…
Let's avoid them, shall we?
避开它们，可以吧？
Excuse me...
失陪…
你就戴这些？
So you'll be wearing those?
有何意见！？
Any objections?
No, but white gloves
for this sort of thing, what an idea!
没有
但戴白手套做这事，真不赖
每人风格不同
To each his own style.
2你不能像其他人一样做事
You can't do anything
like other people.
我们已呆在一起有18个月了
We've been together
eighteen months,
你还是那么客气
and you still stand on ceremony.
我跟母亲，妻子一样的
I'm the same with my mother
and my wife.
这样的话…
In that case...
不，谢了，
我喉咙不习惯英国烟草
No thanks, English tobacco
gives me a sore throat.
没错：手套，烟草…
No doubt about it: gloves, tobacco...
我们没有共通点
We've got nothing in common.
随所欲言吧
Say what you like,
但那里有德国人，
哪里就有秩序
but where there are Germans,
there is order.
没错，那老伙计有点疯了
Sure, the old man is a bit mad
带着他的花盘，
和所有的…
with his flower pot and all...
我在这里的好处之一
A good thing I'm here
to keep those scoundrels in check.
就是时时督查那些坏分子
在家我是个教师
I was a teacher back home.
中尉，
马上没收那些该死的笛子！
Lieutenant, confiscate
those damned flutes at once!
你们最好不要再搞
I advise you not to start again!
15分钟后，我们偏要搞
We'll do just that in 15 minutes.
命令已执行，长官
Order executed, sir.
看到了吧？它发生作用呢？
You see? It worked.
三天内只给面包和水他们吃
Put them on bread and water
for three days. And no parcels.
准备，伙计们，两秒…
Ready, boys... Two seconds...
集合！
Assembly!
我现明白我的学生了
真吵
I understand my students now.
What a lark!
还吵这么久！
While it lasts.
Well...
什么？
What?
Goodbye.
再见了
Boeldieu!
玻狄奥
De Boeldieu!
玻狄奥！
听着！
求你了，下来！
Listen!
I beg you! Come down!
你真的变疯了？
我清醒得很
玻狄奥，玻狄奥！
你明白吗？
如果你不服从我的命令
我得开枪了
我抱歉我要这样做！
下来吧
去死吧
我才不理呢
Lieutenants Mar閏hal and Rosenthal
马利沙中尉和罗斯坦逃跑了
have escaped.
原来是这回事
So that's why.
探照灯
Search lights!
派出巡逻队，带狗！
Send out patrols with dogs!
所有军事，
民事机构提高警惕！
Alert all military
and civil authorities!
每刻钟向我报告情况！
Report back to me every quarter hour!
你命令已传下去，长官
Your orders have been carried out, sir.
目前没有逃犯踪迹
No sign of the fugitives yet.
原谅我
Forgive me.
换了我，我也会这样做的
I would have done the same.
法国人或德国人，
责任是责任啊
French or German, duty is duty.
你痛吗？
Are you in pain?
肚子中了弹并不怎么伤人
I didn't think
a bullet in the stomach hurt so much.
我瞄准的是你的腿
I aimed at your legs.
有500英尺，视野又暗…
It was 500 feet, with poor visibility...
再说，我还在跑
Besides, I was running.
不要这样，没有藉口的
Please, no excuses.
我笨手笨脚的
I was clumsy.
并不是我要受人怜悯
I'm not the one to be pitied.
我们一切都要完了…
For me it will all be over...
很快！
soon.
但你还要继续走
But you'll have to carry on.
继续行尸走肉的生活
Carry on a futile existence.
普通人死于战争是悲剧
For a commoner,
dying in a war is a tragedy.
但你和我
But for you and me,
这是条好路子
it's a good way out.
我错失了机会
I missed my chance.
你不能说太多话的
You shouldn't be talking so much.
长官
Sir...
我们应避开大路的
We should've avoided the road.
我们不能睡在野草里
We couldn't sleep in the reeds.
他走了
He's gone.
难道你没看见它是个女人？
Didn't you see it was a woman?
继续走吧
- Let's get going.
- Wait till dark.
等到天黑再走
冷死了，我得动一动
I'm freezing, I have to move.
要你的糖吗？
Want your sugar?
没剩多少了
There's not much left.
我们还有很长一段路走呢
And we've a long way to go.
你呢？
我吃我的，我饿了
- What about you?
- I ate mine, I was hungry.
你拿着吧，
这样我不至于谗嘴
可怜的东西…
你连纽扣也吃了？
看得出来吗？
那我们不待天黑啦？
我们先沿着村庄走
You keep it, so I won't be tempted.
You poor thing...
You ate your buttons, too?
Does it show?
So we're not waiting till dark?
No, we'll skirt the village fiirst.
你的腿伤了？
无大碍，没什么…
有点僵硬
Your foot hurt?
It's nothing... a nerve.
Let's go.
走吧
你来吗？
You coming?
你来还是怎么样？
You coming or what?
我在尽力呢
I'm doing the best I can.
你和你的脚！
You and your foot!
不是我的错，我摔倒了
It's not my fault! I slipped.
你摔倒了！我只知道这个
You slipped! That's all I hear.
若你导致我们被抓
你就说你摔倒了？
If you get us caught,
you'll explain you slipped?
我们没食物了，
也没力气了
还好，我已经够了
受够我了？
We're out offood.
Might as well give up now.
- Gladly. I've had enough too.
- Had enough ofme?
肯定是，你知道
Damn right! If you only knew
how you make me sick!
我被你搞得很惨
呵，这感觉大家都一样
Well, the feeling's mutual.
你是个累赘，
绑人的锁链
我从来受不了犹太人！
意识到这点有点晚了
很明显，你要死了
你说好！
You're a dead weight,
a ball and chain.
I never could stomach Jews!
A bit late to realize that!
Clear out, you're dying too.
You said it!
迷路！
我讨厌你这丑八怪！
Get lost! I'm sick ofyour ugly mug!
我走了！
你好自为之吧，再见！
I'm going! You're on your own now!
So long!
再见！走吧
So long! Go ahead!
我如此高兴，
我可唱歌…
从前有一条小蒸汽船
它从没去过海洋
I'm so happy I could sing...
There once was a little steamboat
Which had ne-ne-nevergone to sea
海上五至六周后
After five or six weeks at sea
供给几乎用尽…
The supplies
we real-al-almost gone for good...
你为什么回来？
Why'd you come back?
来吧
Come on.
走吧，伙计
Let's go, fella.
够了吧？
还好
- Had enough?
- It's okay.
想去哪树底休息会吗？
- Want to rest in that shed there?
- Too risky.
太冒险了
没有烟啊
这样也不行…
- I can't see any smoke.
- Even so...
船着火时，你往船外走
对，我们往船外走
走吧，老家伙
When the ship's on fiire,
you go overboard.
Right. Overboard we go!
Let's go, old man.
那里有人
- Someone's there.
- The window! Run for it.
那窗！跟到那里去
I'll draw them off.
我去搞定他们
Don't move! Keep quiet.
不要动！保持安静
留在原地
Stay where you are!
French...
说法语的
We're not thieves.
我们不是贼
Prisoners of war?
战争犯？
说德语吗？
You speak German?
我扭了脚，我们累坏了
I sprained my foot. We're exhausted.
We're not thieves.
我们不是贼
我不怕
I'm not afraid.
去叫警察吧
Go on, call the police.
I won't walk another step!
我不会再动一步了
你扭了脚
You sprained your foot?
她说进到房子里边去
不，我不相信她
She says to come into the house.
No, I don't trust her.
她说她孤单一人在这儿
She says she's alone here.
她说她孩子在睡觉，
别弄出声音
She says her child's asleep,
so don't make any noise.
来，坐这里吧
Come and sit down here.
我很快会回来
I'll be right back.
饿了吗？
Hungry? Yes.
她问你饿了没有
我听懂了
- She asked if you're hungry.
- Yeah, I understood.
你呢？
What about you?
我只想睡一下
I just want to sleep.
劳驾，往沃菲斯翰怎么走？
Excuse me, but how far is W鰈fiisheim?
Eight miles.
八英里远
I'd sooner stay here
than slog up there!
去那里，我倒愿留在这里
但是，责任是责任
谢谢了，晚安
But duty's duty.
Thanks and good night.
嘘！孩子在睡觉呢！
Hush! My child's asleep!
My husband.
这是我丈夫
Killed at Verdun.
死在菲尔敦
My brothers...
我的兄弟
Killed at Li鑗e...
死在利格，撒路洛…
唐纳伯格
Charleroi... Tannenberg.
我们最大的胜利
Our biggest victories.
现在这张桌子太大了
The table's too big now.
别紧张，是我罢了
Relax, it's only me!
你不介意一法国人喂你吧
You don't mind
ifa Frenchman feeds you.
你闻起来像我祖父的奶牛
You smell like my grandfather's cows.
A good smell.
好味道
You're a cow from W黵temberg
你是沃滕伯格的奶牛
而我是巴黎来的工人
但我们可以是伙计
你是头可怜的牛
我是可怜的士兵
and I'm a working man from Paris,
but we can still be pals!
You're a poor cow,
I'm a poor soldier.
我们各自尽力
We each do our best.
你是个聪明的小女孩
You're a bright little girl.
妈妈和我是无所不知
Mommy and I know everything.
真的？
Really?
那奶牛每月产多少奶？
Then how much milk
does the cow give each month?
这个妈妈知道
我知道我有10个指头
Mommy knows that.
I know I have ten fiingers.
她要些水
She asked for water.
I know.
我知道
18个月了，
我从未听懂哨兵的话
但她的我听不懂了
For 18 months, I never understood
the guards. But her I understand.
可以，但它看来廉价
我已尽力了
- Nice, but it looks cheap.
- I did my best.
我在跟圣诞老人说话呢
I was talking to Santa Claus.
约瑟夫的胡子真漂亮
Joseph's got a nice beard!
这是圣女玛丽
Here's the Virgin Mary.
我的小驴漂亮吧？
Isn't my little donkey cute?
我的公牛呢？
And my ox?
还有圣婴耶酥
And the infant Jesus...
An ancestor of mine.
我的一个祖先
"Touch?"
as poor Boeldieu would say.
就像可怜的玻狄奥要说的一样
你认为他死了吗？
- Think he's dead?
- Let's not talk about it.
我们不要谈这个
我们准备好了，
叫孩子来吧
We're ready. Go get the kid.
等等…
还有留声机和蜡烛
Hold on...
The gramophone and the candles.
熄灯！
Lights out!
洛特，圣婴耶酥来了
Lotte! Baby Jesus has come.
我知道他会来的
I knew he would!
给我的吗？
Is it for me?
我要小耶
I want little Jesus.
带到床上去？
To take to bed?
不，是吃掉他
No, to eat.
他不是拿来吃的
He's not for eating.
她想吃圣婴耶  ！
She wants to eat Baby Jesus!
绝对不可，甜宝宝！
Strictly forbidden, my sweet!
那我就去吃约瑟夫
Then I'll eat Joseph.
好的，但得在床吃
All right, but in bed.
她要约瑟夫？给你
She wants Joseph? There you go.
你是个好女孩
You're a good little girl.
你的留声机变声了
Your gramophone's on the blink.
"洛特有蓝色的眼睛"怎么说？
How do you say:
" Lotte has blue eyes"?
睡觉去，南瓜
Go to sleep, pumpkin.
我不知怎样感谢你
I don't know how to thank you.
感谢我们？
Thank us?
我们欠你这么多
We owe you so much.
好吧，晚安
Well... good night.
我去煮些咖啡
I'll make some coffee.
咖啡已煮好了
The coffee's ready.
用法语说
Say it in French.
你告诉她我们要走了吗？
Have you told her we're leaving?
还没有
Not yet.
是时候了
It's high time.
你告诉她吧
You tell her.
我们一定得走
我知道
- We must be going.
- I knew it.
马利沙不忍告诉你
Mar閏hal couldn't bear to tell you.
为什么？
Why?
我早知道他会走的
I always knew he'd have to go.
进来吧
Come on in.
有热咖啡
There's hot coffee.
吃点东西再走吧
You should eat something
before you go.
要等到天黑吗？
Do we wait until dark?
要
Sure.
我们去跟牛说再见
Let's say good-bye to the cow.
我孤单得太久了
I've been alone too long.
我等得太久了
I've waited so long.
听到你在房子周围的脚步声
If you knew how happy I've been
你可知我曾经多快乐
to hear your footsteps
around the house.
埃沙…听着
Elsa... Listen.
等战争结束
When war over...
如我还未死
if me not dead...
明白吗？
Understand?
我回到这里来…不
I... come back here... no?
而你…之后…来…
And you... after... come...
跟我…去法国
with me... to France.
和洛特一起去…不好吗？
With Lotte... no?
给你旅途的
For the journey.
快点走，最好这样走
Go quickly. It's better that way.
不望回头？
如望回头，
我可能就不走了
- Not looking back?
- If I do, I might never leave.
走吧
不等天黑了
- Let's move.
- We're not waiting till dark?
我们会迷路的
We'd lose ourway.
树林会掩护我们
The woods will hide us. But in
the valley, we'll have to stay low.
但在峡谷里，
我们得往低处走
你肯定那是瑞士？
You're sure that's Switzerland?
肯定
- Positive.
- It all looks the same.
看起来都一样
You can't see borders.
They're man-made.
看不到边界的，
他们是人造的
大自然也就这样了
Nature couldn't care less.
我想这一切有个了断
I want to see an end to all this.
然后我就回到埃沙身边
Then I'd go back for Elsa.
你爱她？  我想是的
- You love her?
- I think so.
即使我们成功了也要这样
Even if we do make it,
你会回去再开飞机，
我就扛枪
you'll go back to flying
and me to gunning, we'll keep fighting.
我们继续战斗
像那些伙计们
Like the fellas.
We've got to end this damn war...
我们得结束这该死的战争…
让它成为最后一次大战
and make it the last.
不要欺骗自己了
Don't delude yourself.
我们下到地吧？
Let's come down to earth.
What if we run into a patrol?
碰到巡逻队怎办？
We split up, and try our luck.
我们就分开，
大家好运吧
只是以防万一而已
再见吧，希望很快再见到你
再见，你这脏犹太人
再见，你这老东西
just in case, let's say goodbye
and see you soon.
- So long, you dirty Jew.
- So long, you old dog.
别开枪！他们在瑞士境内了
Don't shoot!
They're in Switzerland.
祝他们好运吧！
Good for them!
剧终  谢谢观赏
THE LAST FANTASY